Guide to the Andrew Putnam Hill Photograph Album
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Andrew Putnam Hill photograph album
1887-circa 1895
A0014
Hill, Andrew Putnam, 1853-1922.
5 Linear feet
The images in this album primarily document the Palo Alto residence of Jane and Leland Stanford, the Palo Alto Stock Farm horses, and Stanford University. The university images include the cornerstone laying in 1887, opening day ceremonies in 1891, Encina Hall, Roble Hall, the Library, the Museum, student groups and activities, and various views of campus buildings. Other images include the Alameda in San Jose, palm trees, and prune drying. Many of the university images are also represented in the Stanford University Archives General Photograph Collection.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Biographical/Historical note
Formerly a student of art, Andrew Putnam Hill became a professional photographer in 1889, opening a studio in San Jose, California with his partner, Sydney J. Yard. While his studio produced many individual and group portraits, he also became well known for his views of the Santa Clara Valley region and the Santa Cruz Mountains. He also frequently photographed Leland Stanford's Palo Alto Stock Farm and Stanford University.
Scope and Contents note
The images in this album primarily document the Palo Alto residence of Jane and Leland Stanford, the Palo Alto Stock Farm horses, and Stanford University. The university images include the cornerstone laying in 1887, opening day ceremonies in 1891, Encina Hall, Roble Hall, the Library, the Museum, student groups and activities, and various views of campus buildings. Other images include the Alameda in San Jose, palm trees, and prune drying.
The album has been disbound and boxed. Each page has images glued on both the front and back and has been marked with a plate number. The listing reflects the original captions for the images; information in brackets was added for clarity. Many of the university images are also represented in the Stanford University Archives General Photograph Collection.
Collection Contents
- Photograph Album
  - [Palo Tree (single trunk)]. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Residence of Mr. and Mrs. Leland Stanford looking north (Crandall S-327-16). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Stanford family dogs]: Kaiser, Tootsie, and unnamed. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Tomb of Leland Stanford Jr. at Palo Alto, Cal.; Cactus Garden – Stanford University, Cal. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Residence of Leland Stanford looking west [Palo Alto]. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - In the Grounds [of Stanford residence, Palo Alto]. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Residence of Leland Stanford looking east. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Residence of Leland Stanford at Palo Alto, looking south (Crandall S-327-11). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dining Room, Residence of Mr. and Mrs. Leland Stanford, Palo Alto, Cal. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Library, Residence of Leland Stanford, Palo Alto, Cal. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dining Room, Residence of Mr. and Mrs. Leland Stanford at Palo Alto, CA (Crandall S-327-13). (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Library, Residence of Mr. and Mrs. Leland Stanford, Palo Alto, Cal. [these are slightly different views than plate 5] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Entrance to Art Gallery showing marble hallway and stairs, Leland Stanford Jr. Museum of Art and Antiquity at Palo Alto. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Roble Hall; Encina Hall. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Leland Stanford Junior Museum at Palo Alto, Cal. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Marble Court and Hall, Leland Stanford Junior Museum of Art and Antiquity at Palo Alto, Cal. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interior of Leland Stanford Jr. University Library in 1891 [in pencil: Dr. Jordan's office]; at Roble Hall (Crandall S-310-22). (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Student's room Roble Hall (Crandall S-310-26); Guest's room Encina Hall. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reception Room Roble Hall (Crandall S-310-30); Student's room Roble Hall. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Lobby Roble Hall (Crandall S-310-29); Student's room Roble Hall (Crandall S-310-26). (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Orchestra; Studio [art class] L. S. Jr. U. (Crandall S-310-29). (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Room in Encina Hall furnished by student (Crandall S-310-32); Class of '94. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Reservoir holding water for the L. S. Jr. University, made of concrete, 63 feet high [Searsville Dam]; Above the Dam. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Apricot in Bloom. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General view from the hills looking East; Athletic Field, from Encina Hall, looking west (Crandall S-143-1). (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Looking Toward West Arch [Inner Quad]; Alvarado Row (Crandall S-310-3). (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Encina Gymnasium and Hall; Library, Stan. Jr. University 1891 [in reality, Dr. Jordan's Office; different image than plate 9]. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Library (Crandall S-310-25); Dining room (Encina Hall) (Crandall S-310-31). (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Dining Room, looking from lobby, Encina Hall; [back of Encina Hall]. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - [Inner Quad, before outer quad was built] (Crandall S-310-7A); Stone Chimney Stan. Jr. University 1891. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Laying the corner stone of the Leland Stanford Jr. University May 14, 1887 (Crandall S-141-1); Group of Professors 1981 & '92 (Crandall S-140-2). (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Leland Stanford at the Dedication of the L. S. Jr. Univ. Oct. 1, 1891, reading the address; Dedication Leland Stanford Junior University Oct 1, 1891, Address of James M. McShafter (Crandall S-141-2). (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - West Arch, Interior of Quadrangle; Dedication of Leland Stanford Junior University Oct. 1, 1891, David Starr Jordan delivering his address. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Stanford Jr. University interior of Quadrangle looking east; End of Arcade looking east, Stan. Jr. University 1891. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - From the Hill looking East. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - David Starr Jordan. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Class of '93; Encina Hall, Stanford University [with some male students on steps]. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Encina Hall Stanford University [class of '95 on steps & roof porch]; Encina Hall Stanford University [class of '95 on steps & roof porch, different view] (Crandall S-310-33). (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Lawn Tennis, A Grand Play; Lawn Tennis. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Young Ladies Gymnasium at Roble Hall (Crandall S-310-34); The Tree of '95. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Guest's Chamber, Encina Hall, L. S. Jr. University; Library. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Base Ball Team Class of '95; Professors Row and Encina Hall Gymnasium, club house in the distance; Brood mares with colts in the field, trotting department. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Varsity Foot Ball Team Winners of the Berkeley Contest. (Crandall S-31-024). (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Foot Ball Team Class of '95; Palo Alto Wheelmen (Crandall S-310-2). (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Apricots; Date Palm [not at Stanford]. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Oranges, Palo Alto; Alameda, the once famous drive between San Jose & Santa Clara, founded or built in 1776 by the Missionary Fathers, 3 ½ miles long. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Young palms [not at Stanford]; Alameda, planted by Mission Fathers in 1777, San Jose, Cal. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Rose Tree, Palo Alto; Prune Drying, near San Jose. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - The Paddocks, Palo Alto, Cal [view of Stock Farm]. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - [Stock Farm horses] Advertiser; Electioneer. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - [Stock Farm horses]: Piedmont; unnamed. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Hinda Rose, No. 183 Standard; Sunol in 2 yr. old form. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - [Stock Farm horses]: Electricity (with John Johnson); Electioneer (with Chas. Cochran) (Crandall S-142-3. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Electioneer; Family Carriage (Crandall S-310-27). (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - [Stock Farm horses]: Hugo (Hill & Watkins photo); Advance. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Running Stable, Palo Alto [note in pencil: on former Coutt's property]; Belle Bird. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - [Stock Farm horses]: Rearing Horse; Nephew. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Beautiful Bell (with Chas. Marvin); Sallie Benton and filly. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - [Stock Farm horses]: Hinda Rose; Palo Alto. (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Hinda Rose at 3 years old; Baby McKee. (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - [Stock Farm horses]: Sunol, in December 1891; Sunol, in October 1890. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Beautiful Bells; Bell Flower. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - [Stock Farm horses]: Cooling out after the trot; Electioneer in the lead, cooling horses after speeding. (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - At the Farm [chickens and cows]; the Dairy. (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - [Stock Farm horses]: Cooling out after kindergarten work; Cooling out after kindergarten work [different view]. (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Colts exercising among the trotters; Speeding (Crandall S-142-6). (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - [Stock Farm horses]: In the pasture (Brood Mares); A Corral of Colts ready for kindergarten work. (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Kindergarten colts, waiting their turn (Crandall S-142-3); Learning to Trot; Learning to Trot [different view] (Crandall S-142-2). (Box 4, Folder 34)
Index
Cactus Garden 2
Campus Views 13, 15, 17, 18, 21
Cornerstone laying 16
Encina Hall 7, 11, 14, 15, 19, 21
Jordan, David Starr (portrait) 18
Jordan's office 9,14
Library 14, 21
Mausoleum 2
Museum 7,8
Opening Day ceremonies 16,17
Roble Hall 7, 9, 10
Searsville dam 12
Stanford residence, Palo Alto 1,3-6
Stock farm and horses 21,25-34
Students, including athletics 11, 19, 20, 21, 22